A Guide to the Woodrow Wilson Letters to Richard Heath Dabney, 1881-1926
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Woodrow Wilson Letters to Richard Heath Dabney, 1881-1926
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
505, 542, 9852-i, -j, -k
This collection consists of 112 items (including enclosures).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
#505, #542: Gift of Richard Heath Dabney, 1939 June 3. #9852-i, -j, -k: Gift of Fleming Rutledge, 2007 July 5.
Scope and Content Information
Wilson writes to Dabney, his former University of Virginia classmate (and later history professor at the University) regarding his life after ill health forced him to discontinue his studies.
Of interest are twenty letters, 1881-1889, written after Wilson left the University of Virginia. In them he discusses his law studies, health, the University, the Jefferson Society, fellow students including future University of Virginia professor Charles Kent, impressions of Johns Hopkins and Bryn Mawr, his early writings, marriage, history, and politics. Later letters are shorter and more conventional in content, but contain occasional allusions to public affairs and the presidency.
The collection also contains one letter from Wilson to the University of Virginia Board of Visitors recommending the hiring of Dabney as a professor.
In addition to the letters from Wilson, the collection contains letters or telegrams from Ellen A. Wilson, Edith Bolling Wilson, Newton Baker, John Randolph Bolling, A. S. Burleson, Assistant Secretary of State William Phillips, Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, William Howard Taft, J. P. Tumulty and the Italian ambassador. Most of these letters concern issues that Dabney brought to Wilson's attention.
Contents List
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1881 February 1, ALS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Wilmington, North Carolina, describing Wilson's return to Wilmington after leaving the University of Virginia because of health reasons. Mentions he is still studying law. Wilson also inquires about various former classmates, including future University of Virginia professor Charles "Chucky" Kent, and about events since his departure from his fraternity. The letter is signed "T. Woodrow Wilson." Marked with modern red "UVA library" stamp next to signature.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1881 March 22, ALS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Wilmington, North Carolina, describing the receipt of letters from Dabney and another classmate from the University of Virginia. Wilson describes his attempts at "courting" local girls. Wilson mentions that he is still recovering from his "stomach" illness. He writes of a book he is reading ( Early History of Charles James Fox by George Otto Trevelyan) and highly recommends to Dabney that he read it also. Wilson mentions he is still studying his law books and requests that Dabney write back with news and "gossip" from the University.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1881 April 20, ALS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Wilmington, North Carolina, describing receipt of Dabney's letter, and his apologies for not having answered it sooner. Much of the letter contains questions about various situations at the University of Virginia and his fraternity. Wilson also mentions that Wilmington has "no schools here of any worth at all," and that he is now instructing his younger brother in Latin; his brother is being taught at home because of the lack of good schools. Wilson mentions that he is reading (in Latin) The Life of Cicero. Wilson also mentions the newspaper's account of the death of Beaconsfield and says that Beaconsfield's "scheming" has come to an end with his death. The letter is signed "T. Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1881 May 31, ALS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Wilmington, North Carolina, describing receipt of other letters from former classmates at the University. Wilson comments on the results of competitions at the University at the Wash[ington Society]. He expresses displeasure for the winner of the Oratorical Contest winner, calling him a "greasy junk-shop Jew." The letter also describes the lack of entertainment in Wilmington except for wedding receptions. Wilson contemplates how long he will wait before he "risks his fortunes" and ventures into marriage. He inquires about Dabney's studies. The letter is signed "T. Woodrow Wilson.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1883 January 11, ALS 8 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Atlanta, Georgia, to Dabney in Munich, Germany. Wilson asks about Dabney's studies in Germany and the whereabouts of former University of Virginia students. Wilson tells Dabney that he has spoken before the Tariff Commission. He says he would like to start a group in Georgia, called the "Georgia House of Commons," but for now will be organizing a "Free Trade" group there. Wilson says that young attorneys have a hard time in Georgia because older lawyers are "unscrupulous" in their practice making it difficult for younger attorneys to get started. The letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1883 May 11, ALS 12 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Atlanta, Georgia, to Dabney in Munich, Germany. Wilson acknowledges receipt of Dabney's letter and says that he envies Dabney studying in the "old world" while he is buried in the hum-drum life in "slow, ignorant and uninteresting Georgia." Wilson talks about practicing law in Georgia, and the lack of intellectual companionship he has found there. Wilson hopes to study at Johns Hopkins University. Wilson talks of the election of a new Georgia Governor due to the death of Governor, Alex[ander Hamilton] Stephens. He says that Georgia is too thrifty to have a Lieutenant Governor, and that while the expense of the legislative session and special election would have cost more than a Lieutenant Governor, the people of Georgia are happier thinking that they have saved money. Wilson says that Tennessee offered to send Georgia a candidate to run for governor because Georgia did not have anyone worthy of running. Wilson says the new governor is unremarkable except that he is honest, which Wilson says is rare for politicians. Wilson says the new governor has a speech impediment, stuttering, that makes it hard for him to talk; he quotes someone as saying that they have traded a governor who could not walk for a governor who could not talk. Wilson describes the temporary capital in Atlanta as ugly. If he is not accepted at Johns Hopkins he will go to Baltimore anyway and spend time in that "beautiful" city's libraries. The letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1884 February 17, ALS 8 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Baltimore, Maryland, to Dabney in Berlin, Germany. Wilson writes that he had received Dabney's letter two months previously even though it had been written in July, and had gone through many "notable wanderings" before it reached Wilson. Wilson explains to Dabney that he has moved since the letter was written. He says that he was denied the Fellowship at Johns Hopkins that he wanted, but was admitted as a graduate student. Even though Johns Hopkins is the best place for study at the time, he is disappointed with the school and his professors. He says that if his knowledge of German were better, he would move to be with and study with Dabney in Germany. Wilson also announces to Dabney that he has met, fallen in love with, and become engaged to Ellen Louise Axson, the daughter and granddaughter of a minister. He says she is very intelligent, well read, and "the most domestic of maidens." He notes that she has worked as a portrait painter. Wilson talks of his desire to become a professor, but fears it will be at a school in the West or South, because the job market for professors in the East is difficult. He has not heard from his former classmates from the University of Virginia and inquires if Dabney has heard from any of them. Wilson asks Dabney to notice that he has dropped the "T." from his signature. The letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson." Notes on envelope appear to be in Dabney's hand and read "Answered on May 6th 1884 about his engagement to be married."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1885 February 14, ALS 12 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Baltimore, Maryland, to Dabney in Berlin. Wilson apologizes for the lack of correspondence. Wilson explains that he has not only been made a fellow at Johns Hopkins, but has written a book entitled Congressional Government: A Study in American Politics. He is more content with Johns Hopkins than he was in the beginning. He has accepted a job that involves setting up the history department at the newly-established Bryn Mawr School. He says that he could not refuse the job as it offered a good starting salary and was near the civilized part of the country and good libraries. He mentions his upcoming wedding in June, and offers to introduce Dabney to the new Mrs. Wilson when he returns from Germany. He inquires about University of Virginia friends and refers to Dabney as having an "Old West Range Heart." The closing is "your Loving Friend," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson." Envelope has a forwarding correction to Heidelberg in blue and a pencil notation that reads, "Answered Oct 19 1885."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1885 October 28, ALS 8 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, to Dabney in Bloomington, Indiana. Wilson apologizes for having not written sooner, but explains that Mrs. "W" has been ill. Wilson tells Dabney he is glad to have him back on this continent again, and he feels like he has him back on the East Range again [there is an autograph note by Dabney stating that Wilson meant "West Range"]. Wilson thanks Dabney for his comments on Wilson's book Congressional Government and is assured that Dabney's kind comments are genuine. A large portion of the letter concerns Wilson's happiness since marriage; he describes it as "rhapsody." Wilson congratulates Dabney on having received his Ph.D. in Germany and assures him of its value, and says that he will look out for a job for Dabney. He says that it may be difficult as schools are teaching history in "shamefully small numbers." He ends by saying that the girls at Bryn Mawr are interested and intelligent. The letter is signed "Your Very Sincere Friend Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has the date 18 Dec 1887 pencilled on and is postmarked Dec. 10 Bryn Mawr.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1886 June 6, ALS 4 p. (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania to Dabney. Wilson xplains that his failure to write resulted from intense studying for his Ph.D. examinations at Johns Hopkins which he passed. Expresses his admiration for "Don Miff" which is pervaded with a "true Southern spirit which warmed my heart." He finds the Negro dialect perfect. He wrote a notice of it for the Wilmington papers but doesn’t know if it has been printed. He announced the he is now weighted down with the dignities of fatherhood, although he has not yet seen his little daughter, as his wife was visiting an aunt in Gainesville, Ga., when the baby arrived. He intends to summer in Tennessee where his father is living. Wants to know the fate of Dabney’s prospects at Indiana University.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1886 November 7, ALS 16 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania to Dabney. Wilson is concerned with Dabney's situation at the school in which he is teaching. He has not written for many reasons, one of which is that his baby has been sick. Wilson has been to Cornell to give a lecture and while there visited a fraternity house and spoke to a "brother" who confirmed the situation in Bloomington was as Dabney had written. There is discussion of his teaching methods - "whether that truth be on the side of Webster or of Calhoun." Wilson says that he has an even greater concern since it was he who "advanced his candidacy" for the job at Indiana University. He asks Dabney to write him more about it. Wilson then writes of a Wilmington editor who did not respond to a letter written to him to go along with a "notice" he had written for the paper on "Don Miff." Wilson says that he does not know if the editor even published the piece, but hopes the editor would "play gentleman for once." The remainder of the letter is chiefly about Dabney's opinion of Wilson's moving to Berlin for one to two years. The purpose would be to both learn German and to have some "Leisure time." He inquires how much could he expect to pay for two people and a baby and possible a nurse to live in comfort without a "peppercorn's" regard to style. He asks for Dabney's "whole" opinion. Wilson would like to go now while he is young and his learning abilities are at their best. He asks for Dabney's candid answer. The letter has a P.S. that sends Mrs. Wilson's warm regards and asks for [Charles?] Kent's address. The letter is signed "your sincere friend, Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has the date 1886 pencilled on.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1887 January 25, ALS 8 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, to Dabney at Indiana University. Wilson describes a teaching position that is open at and suggests that Dabney come teach at Bryn Mawr. He states that the cost of lodging will be $7 per week. This is for a third floor room, which Wilson feels is just as nice as the more expensive rooms on the first or second floor. Wilson says that if he and Mrs. Wilson are still keeping house the next year, they would invite him to take a room with them. The salary of $600 a year may be $400 less than Dabney makes in Indiana, but that it is higher than some of the new professors will be getting and Wilson says that there will be a good potential for salary advancement. He says the Quakers who operate the school are cautious and never promise anything, but do as they have means. Wilson says that the region around Philadelphia is good for those who have an interest in history. Wilson writes that he is trying to be careful in suggesting Dabney move because Wilson is unsure if it would be for selfish or unselfish reasons that he would make the suggestion. He describes the Bryn Mawr classes as intelligent and the administration as honest and straightforward. The letter concludes with warm regards from Mrs. Wilson and is signed "Your Affectionate Friend, Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1887 February 17, ALS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson to Dabney. Wilson has received Dabney's letter announcing his engagement. Wilson tells Dabney of his own happiness in his marriage. He says that the good news of his engagement is second only to that of his news that Dabney might be getting a teaching position at the University of Virginia. Wilson writes that he "loves that old place" and the faculty is the most influential in the South. Wilson is resigned to the fact the Dabney will not come to Bryn Mawr to teach as his assistant, but does increase his offer of salary to $850 the first year and $1000 the next. He says that the choice of an assistant is up to him, and while he can't really wait until Dabney finds out if he will be teaching at the University of Virginia, he says it very well might be June when he makes his decision. The letter is signed "With love as ever Your Sincere Friend, Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has the date 17 Feb. 1887 pencilled on.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1887 December 18, ALS 8 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson to Dabney at the University of Indiana. Wilson has been thinking of Dabney often, but was in a small Georgia town for the summer and so out of touch. He was also preparing to lecture at Johns Hopkins as well as preparing for his work at Bryn Mawr. For these reasons, he has failed to write to Dabney. Wilson acknowledges receipt of Dabney's "Memorials of a Southern Planter" about his grandfather. Mrs. Wilson has also read it and they enjoy the "retelling of its contents." Wilson praises Dabney's grandfather and says that he fears this country will never see another such man again. Wilson says all of the North should read this book. Wilson says if there were more people like Dabney's grandfather there would be no "labour" problems because his "conscience was the only kind of arbitrator between master and workman that will ever bring peace and cooperative friendship." The remainder of the letter is information trying to persuade Dabney to come teach at Bryn Mawr. Wilson has increased the salary offer to $1200 or possibly $1500 since the area is expensive to live in. Wilson also writes that the area is ideal for those studying history because of the libraries and such. He ends by inviting Dabney to visit during the holidays. The letter is signed "Your all-the-time chum, Woodrow Wilson." The envelope does not appear to belong to this letter. It is addressed to Dabney at a New York address and is postmarked 1885. It also has pencilled notes which read "answered Jan'y 11th 1888" at the top and in pencil on the bottom portion is written "Something about his marriage." Also in pencil but in what appears to be a different handwriting is the words "this seems to be in the wrong envelope" and a date of 28 Oct. 1885 that has been scratched over in pencil.
- Woodrow Wilson To Richard Heath Dabney 1888 January 20, ALS 6 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, to Dabney in Bloomington, Indiana. Wilson has not written because "things have been at a stand still" regarding the teaching position at Bryn Mawr. Wilson addresses Dabney's concern about whether or not he would be able to break his contract at Bryn Mawr if a better offer came along. Wilson says a previous professor was going to leave, and the school gave him a raise to stay and the promise of no contract. Wilson tells Dabney that the cheapest first class housing he can find would be $16 to $18 dollars per week. Bryn Mawr is trying to build cottages to house professors and Dabney would qualify for them. Wilson also suggests that Dabney take a house in the city and pay $5 per week for car fare. Wilson will continue with inquiries into the matter. He congratulates Dabney on the book he will publish. There is a note added on the first page by Wilson stating that he was sorry Dabney did not visit them over the holidays. The envelope has the date "20 Jan, 1888" pencilled on.
- Woodrow Wilson To Richard Heath Dabney 1888 March 26, ALS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania to Dabney in Bloomington, Indiana. Wilson is disappointed with the negotiations to hire a professor for his assistant at Bryn Mawr. The salary offer has actually now decreased. The offer is $1100 and would require a two-year commitment. Wilson states that is less than what he received when first at Bryn Mawr and that he can not survive now on his $2000 per year salary, except that he gets $500 a year for work he does for Johns Hopkins. Wilson is considering leaving Bryn Mawr to seek better pay and to get a chair teaching public law "or the like" somewhere else. Wilson mentions now having two babies. He thanks Dabney for the copy of his book and promises to read it over Easter vacation. The letter is signed "Affectionately Yours, Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has the date 1888 pencilled on.
- Woodrow Wilson To Richard Heath Dabney 1888 May 16, ALS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, to Dabney in Bloomington, Indiana. Wilson apologizes for not writing sooner, but explains that he has been busy with work and the death of his mother. Wilson writes that his mother's death was sudden and the only news he had of her illness was the notice that she was dead. He says he went to Tennessee to be with his father for as long as his job would allow. Wilson says his father will be alone since Wilson's sisters are all married and his brother is in college. Wilson says her death makes him feel like his youth has also died. He praises Dabney for a piece that he has written to the "University Bulletin." Wilson begs Dabney to please make time to visit him over the summer. The letter is signed "Yrs. Affectionately, Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has " 16 May 1888 about his mother's death" pencilled on.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1888 May 31, ALS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, to Dabney in Bloomington, Indiana. Wilson was glad to receive Dabney's letter of the 22nd. He congratulates Dabney on the announcement of his engagement and his upcoming marriage on June 19. The remainder of the letter is filled with Wilson's praise for marriage. Wilson compares his life before and after marriage, and strongly suggests marriage as a good thing for his friend Dabney. The letter ends by Wilson writing that he would like to have Dabney and Miss Butler spend their wedding trip in Bryn Mawr. The letter is signed "Mrs. and Mr. Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has "about marriage" pencilled on.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1889 October 31, ALS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Middletown, Connecticut, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson sends his sympathy to Dabney regarding the loss of his baby. Wilson writes that being back at the University of Virginia must give Dabney some comfort, as it is so familiar. Wilson asks that Dabney write him with details of his work. Wilson also asks about the textbook that he sent to Dabney. Wilson closes with messages of friendship and sympathy from him and Mrs. Wilson. It is signed "Your Affectionate friend, Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has the date "31 Oct 1889" and "About the death of my wife & child" pencilled on.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1891 July 1, TLS 4 p. (Box 1)
  Wilson, Princeton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson begins by apologizing for having sent a typed letter instead of handwritten but explains his writing pen is elsewhere. Wilson thanks Dabney for the review of his book. Wilson writes a great deal about his friendship with Dabney and what it has meant to him. Wilson closes by urging Dabney to come to Princeton for a visit. The letter closes by saying "As ever of old," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to the Rector and Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia 1897 December 5, ALS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Letter of recommendation from Wilson to the Rector and Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia, requesting that Dabney be given the position of Chair of Historical and Political Science. This is a seat that Wilson notes was vacated by the death of Professor [George F.] Holmes. Wilson describes the service that "sons" of the University have given. The letter is signed "Very Truly Yours, Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has no stamp or postmark.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1899 November 12, ALS 1 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Princeton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson congratulates Dabney on his engagement to a Miss. [Lily Heth] Davis. Wilson regrets that he will not be able to attend the wedding because of work commitments, but assures Dabney he will be thinking of him. Wilson asks that Dabney "Commend" him to Miss. Davis. The letter is signed "Affectionately Yours, Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has the date "12 Nov 1899" and "Congratulating me on my approaching marriage" pencilled on.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1902 October 31, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)